I got to work on whatever I wanted for
my entire career.
>> This is Carrie Notchenberg. He's a cyber
security expert who is a fellow at
Semantic, which is four levels higher
than staff. I look for things with big
business impact. I look where there were
gaps.
>> From there, he joined Google X as a
principal engineer and fought imposter
syndrome. And what if like I'm not good
enough for Google or Meta or something.
>> As a professor at UCLA, he's seeing
firsthand how AI affects the classroom.
>> I allowed students to use LMS. In
retrospect, you know, that was a bad
idea because I think they were using it
in ways that hindered learning.
>> How do you even tell if they're using
LMS, though?
>> Well, the one way you can tell is
>> I learned a lot from his career stories
and hope you do, too.
>> I get this call, a frantic call from
UCLA. Can you still teach? Because our
lecturer bailed on us. I have PTSD from
that experience, I have to say.
Before we get into all the juicy parts
of your career like working at Google X
or autonomous vehicles with Lyft, I want
to start by kind of laying the high
level groundwork. So you worked at
Semantic for a long time and became
their senior most, you know, similar to
a chief scientist type of role. Kind of
want to go over that and all the lessons
you might have learned there and you
know, anything interesting that came up
there. So could you share the highlevel
story arc of you working at semantic and
how you grew to fellow?
>> Totally. So I actually started back in I
think 1992 as an intern at Peter Norton
Group. And so Peter Norton Group was
later an acquisition by Semantic but
some of your viewers are going to
remember Norton antivirus from Norton
and Norton Utilities and so on. And so
um I think I was the first intern at
Norton at Peter Norton computing and
they didn't even have a desk for me. So,
I literally worked in a QA lab with the
QA lab manager who was a guy that used
to sell knives for a living because like
back then in 1982 they weren't
professionally trained software people,
right? So, basically they would just get
whoever knew something about computers
and this guy knew something about
computers to run the lab and I would
work in one of the test computers. Um,
and so that was my first, you know,
summer internship. uh and then fast
forward uh when I left in 2016 I had had
become the senior most engineer of the
company. So from the junior most person
the first intern to the senior most
person at semantic
>> which would had acquired Norton. So it
was a long ride but that that's the high
level. Was cyber security something that
really you were focused and really
wanted a job in cyber security or it
just by chance?
>> Yeah. So at the time when I was working
at Peter Norton Group, I wasn't working
in cyber security. I was working on
something called Norton Commander, which
was like a file utility manager. So I
didn't actually work on cyber security
until my third year, my third year of
internships uh at this point at Semantic
where they they had acquired a product
called I don't remember what it was, but
it was an antivirus product that they
renamed Norton antivirus. So that
product was uh acquired and rebranded uh
and they had a team of people analyzing
computer viruses. So my third year of
internship that's when I got into cyber
security. I had no experience. They just
needed an intern and they threw me on
it.
>> Like what is the the career ladder look
like? Because I think Google and those
companies came in at some point and
said, "Hey, this is L3. This is L4. This
is L5." And then kind of a lot of
companies copied that. At Semantic, what
did career progression look like? I
would say the levels generally track to
companies like Google and Facebook or
Meta or going all the way from like a
junior you know software engineer
through software engineer senior
software engineer staff and so on. So um
the levels are very similar. The
difference was for me at the very high
levels of distinguished engineer and
fellow at semantic you know when I went
to Google they basically said you know
we can't just hire fellows you know we
don't haven't experienced you we don't
know if you're going to do well here so
effectively I was downgraded to a st to
a principal engineer level eight from
what would have been probably a level 10
at semantic it was a vice president role
at semantic
What does the hiring process even look
like for people so high level? Um, was
that a tailored bespoke process? When I
went to uh Google, basically the former
chief operating officer of Semantic, guy
named Steven Gillette, had recently
transferred into Google X and they were
starting a stealth project in Google X,
which we could talk about. he had known
me from my time at semantic and
basically you know said hey why don't
you talk to the team and see if there's
a good fit and so I didn't have to apply
I was just you know brought in and and
uh we had a one meet and greet with the
comp the team's founders uh in Venice
and then we had an interview a day's
worth of interviews probably about eight
interviews and you know six weeks later
I had my offer letter so
>> you know for a lot of software engineers
that are in the lower The interviews are
leak code there or system design and
there's you know some generic behavioral
interview for at the high levels. What
what does that loop even look like? Is
it is it mostly behavioral? Do are they
asking you leak code stuff too?
>> So I don't believe that I had any coding
problems during that interview. I if I
recall correctly there were some design
there was one design problem. Um but
mostly these were leadership-l like
questions like you know how would you
solve a a hard problem or how did you
solve a hard problem in your career um
how do you deal with conflicts um you
know tell me your thoughts on you know
where the field is going you know Google
X is a forward-looking or X rather is a
forward-looking organization and so uh
some of the discussions were focused on
that um some of the discussions were lit
literally sales pitches like I didn't
really have to say they went and talked
to me about where they thought the world
was going to try to get me excited,
>> right?
>> So,
>> I think it probably depends on the
person, but in my case, I think they
thought there was a good fit
>> and it was really about sort of going
through the motions of, you know, having
interviews and selling me on the on the
role.
>> Okay. So, then going back to Semantic, I
mean, you know, g getting promoted to
fellow, what do those highest level
promos look like? At least at semantic,
most promotions up through what was
called technical director or senior
technical director um which would be the
equivalent of let's say staff engineer
or senior staff engineer probably at
other companies. Most of that was done
just within the organization. So as long
as a vice president or senior vice
president was okay with a promotion, it
was it was allowed. uh at higher levels
for distinguished engineer and fellow.
It was there was a a basically um core
group of technologists led by the CTO of
the company. We would meet once a
quarter. Um we would get applications
from those people and we would then
review their applications and actually
have them come talk to us about their
work u and then make a decision based on
that. And so the reason that we did it
that way is that we'd have consistency
across all divisions, all teams, uh, of
what it meant to be a distinguished
engineer or or a fellow for the
organization.
>> Um, so that's the process we went
through and it wasn't just per division,
it was for the company.
>> So when you got promoted to fellow, was
that one of the happiest moments of your
career or was it something you expected,
not a big deal?
>> You know, it was very interesting. So I
did not have to go through that process
to get promoted to fellow. So I was a
distinguished engineer at Semantic. Um
>> and they had that process. I wasn't part
of it because I wasn't a distinguished
engineer at the time. That that team is
made the team of that does promotions is
made up of distinguished engineers at
the time. We had acquired a company
called Veraritoss and Veraritoss had a
notion of a fellow which Semantic
didn't. So basically after the merger
between the two companies, they said
okay we need to level set the role
because the people at Semantic have
never had this kind of role who would
belong there and I was nominated without
my knowledge and it just happened and I
got a congratulations or maybe my boss
filled me and said hey there's some
discussions going on thank you know and
then you're a fellow. So they basically
took my port portfolio of stuff and gave
it to the the team that did the
evaluations and that was the end of
that.
>> I mean with your growth to to fellow
something about the way you work sets
you apart from other engineers. What do
you think are those things for you?
>> I think what helped me get to fellow was
working on really impactful projects for
the business. not necessarily always the
most technically difficult projects
although many of them were but more
impactful like they move the needle for
the company. I had so many of of them
under my belt at that time that they
just said you know the criteria are this
many projects should be done of the of
this scope and I had plenty more and so
they basically said you're you know
you're above the bar. So what was the
what was the key insight to doing those
projects is finding things where there
where there were gaps that you know
things the company needed where people
weren't stepping up to do them and you
know I did them maybe a quick step back
at Savant it was sort of like the wild
west there wasn't an engineering culture
per se there was just people working on
stuff and like projects would often run
really late because you know it was a
little bit more of a wild us. We didn't
have an agile process. Um, we didn't
really do our own unit an integration
task like we'd throw over our code to QA
and they would worry about it and we'd
work on the next thing. And in fact, I
had very unusual circumstances. I didn't
rise to a path where I was given a small
project and somebody said, "Okay, do
this. Here's here's a box around the
project." They basically said, "Carrie,
you already sort of know the technology
because you've been working on it as an
intern. Go figure out what to do and do
it." which was amazing because here I am
like a junior software engineer and I
got to work on whatever I wanted for my
entire career at semantic never assigned
work to do. Yeah, it was crazy, which
was great. And I, you know, and so I got
to just pick projects that I thought
would be impactful. And I picked well. I
got I guess I picked well because I, you
know, project after project landed. They
were integrated. We did tech transfers
into the product, they shipped. So
that's how I got there. It wasn't like,
oh, I did increasingly bigger scope
projects that somebody gave me.
>> So how'd you train that that project
taste? Because impact typically leads to
career growth everywhere. So
>> yeah. Yeah. And it's a good question and
it's I look for things with big business
impact. I look where there were gaps. So
like way back when you know this is like
old news now but it's sort of
interesting like we had um these
computer viruses which are emerging
which were called polymorphic viruses.
They were selfmutating malware and they
were selfmutating in a way that they
there could be like literally
quadrillions of variants and the way
that the teams were working on these
things but back when I was an intern
even is they would basically write uh
handwritten assembly language to go look
for telltale signs of a variant you know
in the mutation. Okay. And the problem
with that is it worked really great
except it took six months because we
shipped a new product every six months.
And so it took six months to discover to
handle a virus and then the next day
somebody released three new viruses
which were slightly you know slight
variance or differences, you know,
different viruses but mostly the same.
And then all of that work would not work
anymore. And so, you know, I would look
at that problem. I'd say, "Oh, there's a
need to be able to move more rapidly in
covering new malware. And by the way,
detecting these selfmutating threats is
not like using a rag X. You can't just,
you know, search for a string to find
these things." So, I'm like, "Oh, that
seems like a really interesting hard
problem." So, I picked it and then I
started working on it. That was my
master thesis and then eventually
transferred to the product. If you were
to think about the things that you took
on, they were a series of I guess side
projects or or you know, whatever you
wanted to take on where you you'd take
on this new thing, maybe something else
would come in, you take that on. Is that
kind of how you were working?
>> I would say there are probably six or
seven times in my career where I'm like,
"Oh, the company needs this type of
thing. Let me go spend six weeks, two
months, five months figuring out what
that looks like, building prototypes,
talking to engineers, and figuring out
what they need. and then you know
building that and there were other times
which is probably 80% of my career where
I was just sort of tweaking those things
in other words we built them we were
trying to either tech transfer it so I
was helping with that fixing bugs
improving those were sort of incremental
improvements on those systems but that
that it's one of those two things
generally
>> so you mentioned a little bit about
viruses and when I was doing some
research I saw that you had done some
storytelling on top of stuckset and kind
of compiled
I think that's such an interesting
story. Uh can you tell me a little bit
about stuckset? Maybe we can go into
that.
>> Sure. Stuckset was um at the time just
unfathomable. It was just a very complex
piece of malware which was
multiplatform. So it didn't just infect
like Mac machines or Windows machines.
It infected I think you know Windows
machines but also like microcontrollers
that would actually run like centrifuges
and so on. Um, and so it was probably
the first multi-platform piece of
malware we had discovered. Uh, use zero
days in order to break into systems that
you know that you know basically
vulnerabilities, exploiting
vulnerabilities that hadn't been patched
because they weren't even known about.
And it didn't use just one of those or
two of those. I think it used like six
different vulnerabilities to spread,
many of which were zero days.
>> My god.
>> Um, it would literally stealth itself.
So on your computer, if you were to look
at a at a thumb drive which had
Snapchatnet on it and look in your your
your Finder application or your Windows,
you know, file system application, you
would see, you know, nothing there, but
it was there. You'd stick that in your
computer, it would auto launch. It
actually had a a payload to auto launch.
If you were to look at the logic that
was running on a centrifuge or rather
the controller that ran the frequency
converters, you would not see any of the
specs in that logic. It was in that
controller. But if you downloaded the
the logic from that controller onto a
Windows machine, it would stealth and
remove the logic from stuckset as it
pulled it off. And then if you updated
that logic, for instance, it would
reinsert itself into that logic to
reinfect it as it went back. So we
actually like sort of piggyback on back
and forth stealth itself. Um it was just
amazing. And then of course how it
disrupted the centrifuges is super
interesting as well.
>> Yeah, it's so complicated and
sophisticated that it makes me wonder
who wrote it and I saw something like it
was, you know, 50 times bigger than the
average virus. Incredibly complicated
software. And I was reading into
Wikipedia a little bit before we kind of
it said no one has claimed credit for
who wrote this thing. Who do you think
wrote this thing? It's
>> I think it's pretty good. You'd be
pretty safe to say it was the Israelis
and the American government. You know,
my understanding or recollection is that
there are water not watermarks but sort
of, you know, coding styles or things in
there that sort of implicate both uh
governments.
>> Have you ever looked at the source code
or played?
>> I have not. I didn't do any analysis on
stuck set. Um my career was focused
early on analyzing malware like
literally looking at the machine
language and disassembling and so on.
But later on in my career it was mostly
about detecting sort knows how how could
I build algorithms to detect that
malware rather than hands-on analyzing
the malware myself. So I'd never looked
at stuckset. Yeah.
>> You mentioned a little bit about uh
assembly code. Did you ever write
assembly code when you were working at
cement?
>> I did. Yeah. I wrote assembly code as an
intern. Um and uh although back in those
days it was mostly C.
>> Yeah.
>> Um but some assembly as well. And I
remember the first antivirus engines
were written in assembly for speed. And
one of my first tasks as I joined
full-time was I said, you know, this
really needs to be a C so it's more
maintainable. So we ported the thing to
C and actually made it faster because
the people back then people didn't know
algorithms. They didn't understand what
an what a big O was or how to you know
they would do linear searches. And so we
were able to go and take something in
assembly language, move it over to C,
have less code, um, and it would be, you
know, five times faster. So
>> I see. So the the speed ups moving from
assembly to C was due to better
algorithms and things like that. It
wasn't because of a compiler or
something.
>> No, the compilers weren't that great
back then. But even without an
optimizing compiler, if you use a hasht
versus or binary search versus a linear
search over 60,000 signatures, you know,
>> I I saw that you worked at Semantic for
a long time and you know, I think in the
tech industry, it's common for people to
move around here and there. What do you
think kept you at semantic as long as
you were?
>> You know, that's a great question. Um,
if I have to be perfectly honest, I
would say imposttor syndrome.
>> Really? So well yes and no. So at
semantic I didn't really have imposttor
syndrome because I had done a lot of
stuff and I was well regarded you know I
was known in the company and so I had a
good safe place but I always worried
what if it just is because I'm at
Semantic and I grew up here and I
learned the stuff here. what if I went
somewhere else and I wouldn't be able to
learn the stuff or what if people had
different standards and what if like I'm
not good enough for Google or Meta or
something and so I stayed because it was
comfortable and I complained I
complained all the time I wasn't happy
later on in my career I have to be
honest with you I wasn't doing things
that made me happy more when you get
more senior you do a lot more BS right
and and and
you also have the opportunity not to do
as much BS but you have to push yourself
not to do it because it's very easy to,
you know, go to meetings and, you know,
have broad discussions and it's not
really that necessarily fun,
>> right?
>> Um, and so I wasn't happy near the end
of my tenure at Semantic, but I was
afraid that I wouldn't be able to do
well or I'd fail the interview process.
And so I just stayed and it was
comfortable. throughout your career
there were so many promotions and you
had so much impact for someone like you
to have imposter syndrome you know I
feel like that shows that a lot of
people you know it's it's a very natural
feeling for a lot of people did you
eventually you did leave semantics so
was there anything that helped you uh
overcome imposter syndrome
>> you know what the thing that that helped
me was that somebody said hey we want to
interview you we think you'd be a good
fit and so I said you Well, I'm probably
going to fail this interview. I'm sure
I'm not good enough, but I'm going to do
it. And so, I just did it. And so, that,
you know, I needed an external pull or
push, I don't know what you would call
it, but in order to get me to to take
the chance, and then it worked out. But
for me, like in my head, I was, you
know, I wasn't competent to do that job.
You know,
>> you you mentioned uh also that at the
highest levels, there's uh, you know, a
lot of BS and, you know, I guess it
sounds like meetings and things like
that. Do you have any uh I guess tips on
how to be less involved in the BS
because I think that's a natural pull
pull for anyone.
>> Yeah, it's sort of natural definitely it
depends what you're doing. I mean some
some tech senior technical directors and
distinguished engineers even fellows
were working dayto-day and building code
and and working with their teams. It
just depended uh I was an individual
contributor vice president. So I was an
IC through my entire time at semantic.
other people would actually manage teams
and work uh more closely on projects.
You know, it's just it's inevitable,
right? In other words, you're having
more strategic meetings and then the
problem is you're having a strategic
strategic meeting with a bunch of
people, many of which many of whom don't
necessarily know that much, but they
have an opinion because everybody has an
opinion. Um, and there's a lot of
debating and a lot of arguing and a lot
of like, you know, posturing for, you
know, for power. And, you know, it's
just there's a there's a lot of garbage
that comes with being more senior,
unfortunately. Like, there was some some
joy, especially for me when I got to
pick my own projects to be able to just
sit down and literally go two months
with nobody asking me what what are you
doing? And, you know, I'm just like
cranking and trying things. That doesn't
work, but that does. And super exciting.
Right.
>> Right. Then you get into a room with
seven people and you're like, "We've
agreed that this is our new company
strategy." One of my last rule uh things
of the company I did was actually define
the company technology strategy for the
whole company. And everybody had agreed
to it. The CEO had agreed to it. And
then we get in a room and everybody
would say, "Oh, sure. But you know, we
have to make money on our projects or
products." And so, you know, adding
those features to align with technology
strategy that's gonna set us back. And
we've been told we have to make, you
know, this much topline revenue. And so,
you know, you end up having debates and
discussions and it's like very very
draining.
>> So, you said you were pulled into Google
X and you ended up taking the interview
and and doing well. I'm curious, what
was it like entering, you know, Google
or this like fang style big tech? And
were there any cultural differences that
stood out to you?
>> You know, few than you would think. I
would say the biggest difference that I
saw there was there were really really
really smart people like semantic had
some smart people but again it didn't
have an engineering culture even when I
left in 2016 it was starting to develop
one but it was really you know it was
more a little looser gooseier than a
Google for sure um but the quality of
the people in Google X and X were really
very high quality in terms of
intelligence now what what seemed about
the same was that many people in X as
there were many people in Semantic
didn't have good taste, research taste
if or or project taste. And so a lot of
people were really smart, but it wasn't
clear that they were picking projects
that would be that would land or you
know or that were feasible in you know
at least in my opinion. So I think
that's a that is an attribute of
engineers no matter what company, no
matter how intelligent um people are.
Um, but it was uh, you know, like it was
it was startling how much how much
brilliance there was. And I do remember
like there was one guy who was clearly
like over a 200 IQ. The guy was just you
talked to him and he was just
astoundingly brilliant and he was still
in L4.
>> Yeah.
>> Why was he in the L4? Because, you know,
he had lack of communication skills. You
know, worked on really interesting stuff
that was interesting to him but not
necessarily had business impact. Didn't
collaborate well apparently. you know,
like there were things, whatever it was.
And it didn't matter that he was
brilliant. Like he was twice as smart as
I was, but you know, just because you
have intelligence doesn't mean you're
going to be successful. And so that was,
you know, saw the same thing there.
>> If I'm understanding correctly, if
you're very ambitious and you really
want career growth, intelligence is not
that important. It sounds like there are
some things that are much more
important. You cited uh communication,
soft skills, project taste, picking
things that actually matter.
>> Yeah. Is there anything else that you
that comes to mind?
>> There are definitely people who are less
intelligent. You're not going to like at
Google we didn't have too many of those
people like there were people that were
really really you know most people were
really quite smart. So I would say a
baseline is you need to have a baseline
level intelligence but I for instance
don't think I'm a really intelligent
person. I I take a forever to learn new
things. I have like this ramp which is
like this you know at least internally
that's how I feel.
>> You don't need that much intelligence be
successful but enough. But um so
communication skills um collaboration
skills are really important like knowing
how to work with somebody and not just
piss them off because you're saying
you're wrong but figuring out how to you
know you know how to how to give them
what they need in order to get what you
want which by the way I haven't really
mastered yet. I've screwed that up a
bunch of times too. But that's one like
we talked about business outcomes. I'll
generalize that. I would think something
that's really important to move up is
focusing on outcomes. So this is like a
really important thing and I probably
did some of it subconsciously or
unconsciously and some of it after I
learned about it more consciously. It's
very easy for people to focus on their
own outcomes. In other words, they know
what they'd like to do. They know about
the technology they want to build. They
know that they want to make it 10%
faster or whatever it is or but often
the outcomes of the company or the
outcomes that somebody else is trying to
meet are different than your outcomes.
And if you don't project yourself into
their shoes or the company's shoes and
identify what the company's outcomes or
divisional outcomes are or the other
team's outcomes are, people are not
going to be interested in what you have
to do, even if it's really complex and
hard and interesting for you. And so I
think what really helps far more than
intelligence is focusing on what
outcomes need to be solved for a project
or for the company. What metrics matter
for those outcome? Because often there
are things that don't really matter that
much like you know there are like
requirements that are unimportant and
requirements that are super important.
So focusing on the most important
requirements and doing that work and
focusing on the most important outcomes
for your division or company and then
focusing on the only the most important
requirement is going to get you far much
farther than being intelligent. I would
say
>> I I think you you have an interesting
perspective because you're in academia
because you're lecturing at UCLA, but
you've also had uh a lot of success um
in the in the industry as well. When I
was in school, everything was very
obviously uh intelligence-based. Maybe
unless there's a uh well, aside from
hard work, but you know, you're there's
a test. You either get it right or or
not. aside from group projects and
things like that obviously coming from
that place you know intelligence feels
like everything and then you get to
industry and I agree with you 100%
intelligence is not everything in
industry but because in in college it's
very obviously meritocratic whereas in
industry there's other things too like
do people like you or uh you know other
things like that would you say that
career growth is meritocratic in the
industry
>> you In my experience, it was the there
were cases where people were being
promoted because a vice president
basically pushed really hard or SVP
pushed really hard and said, you know,
they need to be promoted, period.
Otherwise, we're not going to be able to
keep them. And that's never a good
reason to promote somebody, right?
Because you don't uphold standards that
for everybody else to look at and then
you end up with a bunch of people that
are not great and everybody's like,
well, why shouldn't I be promoted
because that clown is promoted, right?
Um but by and large I would say it was
meritocratic. You know I remember when I
was on these committees we would look at
the accomplishments and the complexity
of the accomplishments the impact that
they made uh for the company. We look at
the communication skills. We looked at
for instance patent portfolios. Were
they helping the company with
intellectual property um which was
important back then I don't know how but
important it is now but um so it was
generally pretty fair and I saw Google
too. It was very fair. there were, you
know, very reasoned discussions about
each person. So, I think it is. I think
it is. It's just it's not just, you
know, you ever see those charts where
they have like a circle and then they
have like little like a sort of a
polygon inside, right? Right.
>> And it shows like how your intelligence
is versus how your your technical work
is
>> and it had to be pretty, you know,
pretty wellrounded for the senior levels
or or at least be really good in some
areas. So then at Google, you went to
Google X working uh in a new cyber
security division and then a company was
spun out of that, right? Chronicle if I
recall correctly, but it's still under
the alphabet umbrella of companies.
>> That's right.
>> Which was then reacquired by Google
Cloud. Could you share a little bit more
about that story?
>> Yeah, sure. So we started as a stealth
project. Nobody knew we were doing cyber
security initially. The project name was
Project Lantern and this is inside of
Axe. Um, and we literally started from
zero. We didn't know what we wanted to
build. There were lots of debates and we
knew generally what we wanted to do. But
we spent, I think, a good six months
trying to just figure out what we were
going to build. We then basically
converged on an idea. We started hiring
a bigger team, started working on, you
know, building prototypes of the product
out. Finally got to an MVP, started, you
know, shipping, working with partners,
um, which was great. You know, actually
seeing real customers use it was super
useful. and seeing their we would we
would actually go into customer sites
before we had the product and just watch
how they did their work and saw where
they struggled which was super useful.
Um really interesting actually like
watching cyber security teams work. Some
of the people were like stoned you know
they're clearly out of it you know like
these are the people that are using your
product you know for better or worse.
>> So the product was a product that cyber
security engineers would use.
>> Yeah. So best way to think about in a
nutshell about Chronicle's product which
was called backstory was basically cyber
security today is a big data game. Okay.
And what you what you want to do,
especially if you're trying to discover
attacks in your environment or
investigate attacks, which is a big part
of cyber security, some of it's
proactive, some of it's blocking the
attacks before they come in, but a lot
of it is they're going to get in and we
have to know where they are, when they
got in, what assets they access, and so
on. And so, as it turns out, virtually
all software and hardware that's used in
corporations today generates huge
amounts of logs. A firewall will have
every connection, the source IP, the
target IP, what protocol. Web proxies
will tell you what websites were
visited, uh what what again what machine
visited them. You have telemetry like
DHCP that tells you like what machine
what machine IP is associated with the
MAC address, associated with the machine
name. You have email logs. You have
client logs, what software was
installed, right? All that data is super
valuable for identifying attacks. Okay?
But there's such high volume of that
data that people couldn't really process
it. And so the customers that we were
starting to work with would use a
competing product which I won't name but
they would literally go they would
ingest a certain fraction of that data
very little of it because it was so
expensive to maintain it and they would
go for coffee for 30 minutes while
waiting for a query to finish to look up
just one piece of information in that
data. And so we said, look, we have
Google planet sized uh compute, you
know, and storage. How could we totally
turn this around? And what we did was we
built a product that would ingest all
that data, pabytes of data, like
literally some for some companies, a you
know, pabyte a week or a pabyte a month,
a huge amount of data of, you know,
every device, every connection, every
file installation, every settings
change, like all that kind of stuff. And
then we indexed it. That's what I worked
on. That was my sort of you know
addition like so that it would be more
like uh at the speed of a Google search
than a 30 minute let's go get some
coffee. What would be a use case? Let's
imagine that you discovered a piece of
malware on a computer. Uh you might have
a hash for that malware. You might know
the IP address where it came down from
or was downloaded. You might have the
file name. You might know the directory
was installed. Our product would allow
you to take any of those artifacts and
plug it in and then we would instantly
tell you which devices also had that
artifact on them, what related artifacts
there were to that, you know. Um, so you
could say, "Oh, well, this file had a
different name even though it had the
same hash, let's say." And so we know
better check for this name because this
might be on some other computer. So you
could pivot. Um, we could tell you how
many devices were impacted in your
environment, who's those devices were,
when was the first infiltration, when's
the last infiltration, is it still
active, and do that in like 2 seconds,
you know, that kind of those kind of use
cases.
>> Wow.
>> As opposed to 30 minutes where, you
know, um, hopefully it gives you an
idea.
>> You know, when it comes to Chronicle,
even just doing the research, I got a
little confused. Sounds like it it spun
out and then it came back in. What's
What is the the benefit of doing that
stuff? Why not just do it, you know,
within Google? And that's kind of that.
>> That's a great question. So, I think X's
initial goal was to create viable
businesses, you know, that could spin
out and, you know, be world changing.
Okay. And so, we were following that
playbook, which was, hey, let's incubate
it. Um, let's get really good people to
work on it. We had really smart people.
um let's not en encumber the team as
much as we might a normal Google team.
Let them work fast. Let them do what
they need to do and then let's spit it
out. You know, I can't really talk about
why they required it. Partly because I
only have hypothesis I don't know, but
let's just say that it was a tight fit
with Google Cloud. In other words,
Google Cloud offers services to
customers. This was a cloud hosted
service. It used a lot of storage and a
lot of compute which by the way Google
cloud had and Google cloud could build
for right and so I think that for
various reasons which I can't talk about
after we spotted out we were still an
alphabet company like Whimo okay so we
were still like a under the alphabet
umbrella we were the C in alphabet for
Chronicle um but I think they thought
you know they had competing products
they wanted to integrate them there were
a bunch of reasons that they brought it
back in and sort of integrated it so we
were for a time not part of Google. You
know, for instance, Google, I don't if
you ever heard, but Google performance
are notoriously lengthy and timeconuming
and you have to write pages of stuff
about yourself and what you did and PRs
that you did and all the all the stuff,
right? At Chronicle, we're like, we
don't want to waste time on that. We
want to build a project. So, as soon as
we spun out, we had one page performance
reviews and I think they were in a
Google slide. It wasn't even like a big
page of written stuff. So, so we could
move more quickly, you know, and so that
was great while it lasted.
>> Why is it that you eventually left
Google?
>> That's another one which has to do in
part with imposttor syndrome is a
regular thing in my career. And in part
it has to do with wanting to work at a
startup as opposed to in a a bigger
stodgier sort of Google environment
whereas things are more slower moving
and there's more regulations and things
you have to deal with. Not that we
didn't have to deal with those things in
Chronicle, but more so. Um, part of me
didn't feel like like there were
interesting problems that I could have
done. For instance, the storage
architecture that we came up with, part
of which I built and I think my code's
still in there. I feel very proud of
that. Um, you know, six, seven years
later, whatever it is. Part of that was
an architecture which was very expensive
and there were ways to basically move
that into different file formats and get
off of things like Spanner which was you
know very heavy weight where I could
have dived in and tried to solve those
problems and they'd be nice big juicy
problems. um I didn't have the
confidence in myself to do that and I
you know I was afraid especially when
you get to senior levels there are very
high expectations for you right and so
like if you go off and try to do
something and then people are like well
what have you been doing the last couple
months and it didn't land and like
you're like oh I tried you know I didn't
feel the confidence in our leadership
that I could go off and take those risks
and have them have my back at semantic I
did like I knew my bosses for years and
so they they just knew that if I were
going to go do something I'd either be
successful or if I failed it was for a
good reason and they'd give me the rope.
Okay. But at Google, I didn't quite feel
like I had that. And they offered me
other roles, too. They said, "Oh, you
want to work on secure databases." Um,
there were some really interesting
things there of like how do you compute
and do database queries entirely in
encrypted space rather than decrypting
and doing it, you know, basically taking
private data and exposing it where
malware or other attacks get to it or
interesting things. I really wanted to
try something new sort of over cyber
security and while I was at Axe I was
talking to all the Whimo guys especially
before Whimo even became Whimo and I was
learning all about self-driving cars and
so that was what I really wanted to do
and that's why I decided to leave.
>> Yeah. Before we get into the
self-driving cars, I'm curious cuz I
talked to someone who felt uh the the
high expectations of the highest levels
was a little bit limiting or kind of put
too much pressure on them and they
requested a demotion. Did you ever
consider something like that?
>> Not semantic. At semantic, I could do
whatever I wanted to and it didn't
really matter like you know.
>> Yeah. But but at Google I had thought
about those types of things actually you
absolutely came to mind. The problem is
that even at lower levels, there's
certain expectations
that I probably wouldn't have met if I
want to go off for a couple months and
just think about something and which is
the way I've been most successful in my
career.
>> And so, you know, I got to be honest
with you, um I'm a loosey goosey kind of
guy. like I can produce prototypes and
and optimize algorithms and do you know
relative interesting stuff but when it
comes to dotting every eye crossing
every tea making sure I test every edge
condition in my unit tests that's not my
thing I don't enjoy that but at a Google
that's just like that's what you do and
so for me that wouldn't that wouldn't
have necessarily made a difference
because I would have had to do the
things I didn't like to do in order to
do the things that I wanted to do
>> okay going into autonomous vehicles so
you went to it sounds like that was
mostly because of personal interest in
the space. Can you talk about how you
were hired and the story behind that?
>> Sure. So, at Lyft, um I actually had a
former student from UCLA that was
working at Lyft and he said, "Oh, you
should come work here. It's really
interesting." And I thought, "We'll
never hire me because I actually tried
to apply for Whimo when I was in Google
in X." And you know, again, this is
another problem with being very senior.
when you're very senior and you don't
have domain expertise in a new space,
they're less likely to say, "Oh, we'll
take a we'll we'll try you because
you're very expensive, right?" And, you
know, you might not have the skills that
they need, and you know, they're paying
somebody that they they can't use. So,
Whimo didn't want me inside of Google or
Alphabet. So, I said, "Well, they're
probably not going to want me because I
don't have any experience here, but why
not?" And so, uh, my former student
arranged a meeting with their president.
We had had uh coffee and then I went
through a set of interviews again 78
interviews. Those did have some coding
um and design problems. Um that went
fine. Fortunately, there was no dynamic
programming because I can't do that. I
mean just can't like you know maybe
certain cases I can but you know I'll
fail every dynamic programming interview
uh question. I was hired.
>> What were the projects like or what was
the thing you were most interested in
working on that you did? So for me the
big project that I sort of was proud of
was transforming the architecture
um from one which was a classic robotics
architecture like you would have seen in
the you know even in Whimo until
probably the mid mid little middle 2010s
which was largely handwritten algorithms
and you know sort of not expert systems
but handwritten algorithms that would
make decisions like oh it's time to do a
left turn let's run the left turn
decision decision making system and
figure out is it safe? Do we initiate?
Do we not initiate? Um those systems you
know in the mid210s were using um neural
networks but they were only using it for
vision. So in other words you know you
know recognizing vehicles pedestrians
and so on maybe their you know their you
know angle and so on and their and their
velocity and acceleration. But at Lyft
they were using that sort of earlier
approach which I'm sure came up through
places like Carnegi Melon where a lot of
it was handcoded and to me I looked at
that especially during my time at X
seeing neural networks and semantic even
seeing neural networks and said there's
got to be a better way because if you
start hard coding an algorithm to figure
out how to do a lane change and then
somebody swerves in front of you now
you're doing an avoidance maneuver right
now avoidance maneuver do you switch out
of your lane change algorithm in order
to do an avoid avoidance algorithm or do
you stay in lane chain and handle
avoidance it just made no sense and so
you know uh the team was also h the
stack was also hand parameterized so
literally you know we they're twe how
diff how close do we want to get to the
curve you know um okay how close are we
willing to get to pedestrians what about
bicyclists what about you know what okay
so if we get too close to a bic
bicyclist today let's tweak that and
make that bigger but wait a second now
it's gonna affect our our curb distance
and so like there
you know, a hundred parameters that all
had to be tweaked and it was a really
difficult problem. And by the way,
companies like Tesla were doing this
until recently too
>> that that approach and Whimo was doing
that um for a long time, is a dead end.
Uh it's a dead end. And so the approach
that you know I think that probably
Whimo is using now I don't know but my
guess is uh and I know that Tesla is now
using they've announced it is you know
an endto-end uh neural network-based uh
perception and behavior planner system
and prediction. you know, basically all
them, you know, there might be multiple
heads on these neural networks and there
multiple functions that they're they're
performing, but effectively it's a
single or small number of networks
working together to figure out the the
movement. And so figuring out doing and
doing a lane change is not necessarily a
lane change algorithm, although there
may be a little bit of that, but it's
mostly about, you know, we know we need
to go there. We know there's a left turn
lane. Let's, you know, let's start
maneuvering into the left turn lane and
turning on the signal. And so my pro the
project that I was most proud of there
was basically designing with the head
roboticists of the team were who are old
school by the way an architecture which
would accommodate basically an endto-end
neural networkbased driver but put guard
rails on it. In other words have a
safety layer that would ensure that if
the network went off the rails and told
it to go through a red light we would
slam the brakes. The safety layer would
take precedence over the the system. But
the safety layer was there only for
basically ensuring you know that
collisions never happened. Basically
bringing you to a safe shop or basically
you know following legal rules that the
neural network may not do perfectly.
Does that make sense?
>> Right. That makes sense.
>> And so that was that was I was very
proud of that project. Unfortunately
this is a this is like a bit painful for
me. I didn't get as much credit for that
as I I would have liked given the work I
did which is like one of the things I
learned is like you really have to toot
your own horn. you have to really talk
about what you're doing. Somebody else
took credit for a lot of that. But the
hard and really great part of that was
this was no coding really. This was all
about working with roboticists who did
not want to change the approach and
getting them to consider a new approach,
working together to define the approach
together rather than telling them how it
should be because I didn't quite know.
But by the way, I I thought I had a
better idea, but they didn't want to
hear that because I had no degree in
robotics. and then eventually coming up
with a product that was a collaboration
where they were able to buy in and push
it themselves if that makes sense.
>> Right. Right.
>> And that was all like, you know,
influence and not because I and
influence but not based on my skill
because I don't they didn't have any
autonomous vehicle skill.
>> I think that's a common topic that
people wonder when they're doing shared
projects is how do you make sure you get
credit for what you worked on? And so
maybe you could talk about that. I wish
I had a good recipe for that. I, you
know, in general when you're when you're
more junior, I think it really makes a
lot of sense in the moment when you
finish a project or you're you're almost
done with it to take notes on what you
did and what the big accomplishments
were and what the metrics were so that
when it comes time to write up a promo
packet or even, you know, your sort of
yearly review packet, you have all those
details which you're going to forget
later on even like two years later when
you're going up for more senior promo,
right? So having that I think is useful.
To be honest with you, I never did that.
But like in retrospect that wouldn't
have been very useful for me because I
would come out of it from my head and
then ask people like what was that? How
much faster was that? Like what what now
was able to detect that we could have
detected before? But I think that does
help a lot and you have to toot your own
horn like you know when you're when
you're writing your performance review
without embellishing. I think
embellishment is really bad actually.
But, you know, really state what you did
and the value added and the sections
that you worked on. Don't claim credit
for everything. Claim credit for the
parts that you worked on because I
guarantee you when a committee is
reviewing your packet, they're going to
be like, "Wait, why are they taking
credit for all this when we know that so
and so did all of this great work?" And
then you lose credibility. So, um,
because I've been on those committees,
right? I've seen that. I've seen that
happen. So, you know, be very specific
and granular about what you did, what
the benefits were, how you collaborated.
Um, I think that helps a lot. When
you're more senior, it's more difficult
because it's it's a lot of soft power.
It's a lot of, you know, influence. I
was actually reluctant like I didn't
even try to take credit because I didn't
want to alienate my co- collaborators
who also were part of this. And so, I
didn't go around and start teles talking
to the president saying, "We've come up
with a new approach." I let them talk
about it. I let their boss talk about it
and that actually hurt me because I
never got, you know, when it came to
review time, they said, "Oh, their
manager initiated this project." I'm
like, "What?" Like,
>> really? This is news to me.
>> Oh, no. So,
>> yeah. Yeah. So, that was very I have
PTSD from that experience, I have to
say.
>> Uh, before we leave Lyft, I'm kind of
curious. Um, because that space is super
competitive. there's like,
>> I don't know, a billion different
self-driving companies, especially back
then.
>> Um, what did it look like for Lyft to
kind of win in that space?
>> You know, it wasn't clear that we had a
strategy to win in that space. We were,
you know, definitely a nent
organization. I think they'd been around
a couple years when I first started
versus like 10 years for for Google and,
you know, X working on that technology
and then Whimo. So, um, I didn't go in,
for instance, thinking that I would be
building the next generation of
self-driving car that would actually
overtake a Whimo. I I went in thinking
this is an opportunity to learn
something new and work with really smart
people. Um, and that was my outcome that
I was trying to achieve. Um, so I don't
know if there was a plan necessarily.
And the division was eventually sold to
a Toyota uh subsidiary. So, they got the
IP, which is great for them. And you
know, at that point, I said, "Okay, I'm
retiring now."
>> You know, I'm kind of curious because
how did you get into actually becoming a
professor at UCLA and lecturing there? I
know you get a lot of joy out of it.
What's the story behind going back and
and lecturing? So, back when I was in my
late teens, early 20s, I was teaching
programming in a place called Learning
Tree, which you probably have never
heard of, but Learning Tree is a
for-profit school where they will teach
you gardening, guitar, knitting, and
back then they started teaching
programming. And it wasn't very easy to
find people who could teach programming
because it was early. That was probably
in uh 1990 1991. So I applied because
one of my friends was doing it and I
really enjoyed it and I was teaching
people from Dvry. You ever heard of Dry?
>> Oh, I've heard of that.
>> They used those commercials, right?
Well, they were trying to learn from me
a learning tree so they could teach at
DVY back then because they didn't even
have a programming class there,
>> right? Okay. So, I've been teaching
people and really enjoyed it and it felt
really good to uh uh get up in front of
people and explain things and try to be
really clear and uh so I had had some
experience doing that. And at UCLA when
I was in undergrad uh I would teach
little classes. We found a room in the
evening and I just invite people who had
problems with some of the material and
we'd just go over it on the whiteboard
together or blackboard. Um so I enjoyed
that kind of stuff. And when I was at
Semantic, one of my colleagues was uh a
guy who was a part-time lecturer at
UCLA. We were having lunch and I said,
"Oh, you know, I really enjoy teaching
and he's like, "Oh, you should apply."
And I'm like, "UCLA would never hire me.
I don't have a PhD. It'll never happen."
And I uh he said, "You know, let me
bring you an application just in case."
And I said, "Okay, whatever you want."
And like a couple days later, he brings
this application. He's like, "Here."
Filled it out, gave it back to him.
Didn't hear anything for months. I don't
remember if it was 6 months, a year, I
don't remember how long it was. And two
weeks before fall quarter of 2001, so
like December of 2000, I get this call,
a frantic call from UCLA, can you still
teach because our lecturer bailed on us?
And I said, of course. So I had two
weeks to plan a curriculum and basically
teach undergrad course at UCLA. And you
know, it's 25 years later now. So
>> I'm very glad that they did end up
picking you because you are one of the
best lecturers and I think so a lot of
my peers think so as well and that's why
I kind of want to ask you how do you
make these CS lectures so engaging and
interesting.
>> Well first of all it's very kind of you
to say that. Um so there are a couple
things that go through my mind. So first
thing is remember I told you I didn't
think I was that smart. So I think
whatever intelligence I have and
whatever that is whatever level that is
helps me write better lectures because I
feel like unless I could understand
something myself being I think sort of
slow other people can't understand it
too and so I try to design lectures for
what I think is one of the lower common
denominators which is myself and I don't
try to teach to the top 5% of the class
maybe that's a problem for some people
but I try to teach for the maybe the
30th percentile or 50th percentile and I
think like what would what what what
would I want to know if I were being
taught this for the first time? I try to
have empathy for the student. I think
like where are they coming from? What
have they learned about? Have they do
they even know this concept? Should I
introduce this first before I do that?
So I think a lot about like I try to put
myself in their shoes and ask what would
they know? What concepts were they going
to be fuzzy at versus concepts I'll
pretty have pretty solid where I can
just use the concept and explain it. And
so that's a lot of what goes into my
lectures. And so just for now, like I'm
I'm trying to prove some slides. I'm
literally spending days back and forth
with chat GB03 discussing concepts and
trying to simplify it so much but still
get the essence right and then I'll go
to Gemini and verify see figure out
where they have differences and then
I'll because there's a lot not a lot of
materials on the internet that are
actually really good to be honest with
you. Um and the textbooks all suck too.
I have to say we talked about outcomes
earlier and for me an important outcome
is that students not only learn
something but enjoy the process. They
don't I want them to have a good time
and so I'm always thinking when I'm
making slides, can I make them funny?
Can I make some some joke or something
silly? Can I make them like sort of
colorful or you know add like an emoji
or something to make it a little bit
more fun so that they there's just a
little bit of surprise when they come to
class. They never know what they're
going to see. might be a little
inappropriate, you know, might be a
little silly because I don't just want
them to learn. I want them to learn and
enjoy. They want to come to class.
>> One one thing I'm also curious because I
think a lot of people are scared of
public speaking, but I you know, you're
you're very good at it. Do you have any
tips on on speaking well and
>> practice just practice a lot? The more
you do, the more fluent you're going to
get. I even find like when I'm not
teaching, because I'm part-time teaching
right now, I'm retired. and I'm taking
my dog for walks and working on side
projects, playing with LLMs and stuff.
Um, and I find that my speaking
deteriorates over time when I'm not
actively using it even over the course
of a year. That might just because I'm
getting older or whatever, but in in
general, I found it too like earlier in
my career. So, if you want to get better
at presenting, if you want to get better
at communicating, um, you have to
practice a lot. And so that might mean
getting a lunchroom and giving a talk
about a project you're working on so
that you can explain to other people
what you're doing even if you don't need
to. You're not doing it because it's
required to transfer over your project
or to integrate some technology just to
do it. And people love that, by the way.
And you'll probably screw it up the
first couple times. You'll get better
and better at it. And eventually you'll
find that people will listen to you and
take you more seriously if you're a
great presenter, a great communicator.
And in fact, story really quickly back
to my time at Google X. Um, I remember I
actually had a talk that I used to give
at Semantic and I got permission. It was
on stuck dad, I think, and on maybe
malware detection. I had another one and
I got permission from Semantic to give
that talk in privately inside of X. And
I remember people coming up to me
afterwards and saying, "Wow, you know,
you're one of the smartest people I've
ever met." I'm like, "Little, you really
don't know." But people will think
you're intelligent and they will give
you more credit and they'll introduce
you to other opportunities based on your
ability to communicate because people
associate that with intelligence if that
makes sense. Um and like I can go into
endlessly about times in my career where
communicating effectively helped my
career. So it's super important. But
yeah, practice
>> you know with all the LLM and you know
AI coming in are you seeing people cheat
more often with LLMs? Are people
learning less or more? uh last year in
fall I allowed students to use LLMs not
to write the whole project but for
autocomplete or to write simple you know
parts of the project which weren't
really relevant to the material that we
were covering and I think in retrospect
you know that was a bad idea because I
think people were autocompleting a lot
more than just like a function uppercase
a string or something you know like that
kind of thing, you know, they were they
were using it uh in ways that hindered
learning. I've recently been reading a
bunch of papers about how it helps in
Hindu's learning and actually I don't
know if you saw this recently a study at
MIT that like synaptic connections are
down from like 70% to 50% or something.
Uh I forget the numbers but like I just
saw a blurb when people use LM to solve
a problem rather than working through it
themselves. So I'm actually this coming
fall I'm going to allow LLMs for
learning like clarifying concepts asking
for what what does this mean? But I will
not allow them ideally for projects
because I believe that it did hurt
understanding and we saw that in exams
like if you look at the exam
understanding versus project scores
there's a big delta perfect project
scores but uh getting everything wrong.
>> Although I have to say the projects were
not solvable entirely with all those but
you you know the latest models now you
could probably get a 95% on on uh on
them with really bad code but we weren't
we evaluating correctness not code. How
do you even tell if they're using LMS
though?
>> Um, well, one way you can tell is that
when they autocomplete, often they'll
autocomplete. These LMS will generate
error checking, right? The error
checking will typically have an
exception with an error, a message, and
the messages will be very consistent
across different implementations.
>> And so, in fact, we have cheating
software that checks n squared
different, you know, everybody's project
against everyone else's project. And we
will have flags where it's like 30% of
this code is similar and a lot of it is
like word for word similar error
messages and similar variable names and
you know like similar idioms and so like
pretty obvious people are using these
things extensively.
>> You know a lot of people are worried
about LLM's kind of automating software
engineering and you know should they
even get a software engineering degree
anymore? You know what do you think
about that? It's a great question and I
and I think that it depends on what
these models evolve into. Imagine you
could literally give a project to an LM
just like a junior engineer and it would
produce a component which is largely
correct with tests with security
factored in with proper modularity DOI
all the other good stuff you want. If we
get to that point where bigger and
bigger tasks of more complexity are
solved correctly with good style and not
no code smell and all the other good
stuff that that is let's call that like
AGI programming for for a time being for
the time being. Contrast that with what
we have today which is a models that can
actually solve tightly specified sub
problems pretty well build tests for
them but you still need some you know
some supervision you know did it use a
good algorithm did it like do a deep
copy when it should have done a shallow
copy of a data structure like all this
stuff like this right I think if we stay
in a world where we get really good but
not AGI good based on that definition I
gave you earlier I think software
engineers uh software you know software
engineering will still be a great field
to get into because someone is going to
have to go and look at that code and
understand the mission of the company
and understand the standards and so on
and then make sure that it's doing the
right thing and that requires real
thinking and introspection and
corrections and you know and even if you
have the model fix things you still have
to know what to have fix um and so I do
think that having that degree and having
the skill of be able to write code and
read code is super valuable and we could
talk about if you want like but what
about all the jobs going down right now
you know if that which may be caused by
the by LMS probably in part so that
that's one situation the other situation
if you truly have an AGI where you can
go and delegate something to it and it
will do like a L5 job it will do a
really good job it might need a little
bit of couple tweaks but they're minor
tweaks takes on projects that would take
weeks just gets them done um I think the
world's a lot different and I and and in
that world where literally all the
software of whatever complexity can be
written correctly securely with right
tasks. Uh I think all bets are off and I
think it's a different a different set
of skills that are necessary personally
and I can tell you what I think those
are but I think it's different.
>> What what are those skills? Project
management soft skills those things.
>> So in a world where software can be
written like arbitrarily complex
software can be written tested you know
good style everything is you know good
stuff like you'd expect of a senior
engineer. To me, the world changes into
a place where you're the where engineers
are going to be focused and maybe
they're not even engineers anymore on
what we build, not how we build it.
Okay? So, what problem are we solving?
Why are we solving it? I think of in
that world, the greatest engineers will
be people who really understand a
problem that they're trying to solve for
a customer. That might be an internal
customer, might be a customer that
you're like a consumer, might be a
business, and you know exactly what
pains they're facing and how they
measure success and what gets them
really pissed and what is hard for them
to do now and you want to make easy. And
then figuring out how to really clearly
communicate to an LLM those requirements
to get it to do all that hard
programming work that you would have had
to do over weeks and months. And that is
a really hard problem in its own right.
So if people who have really great
clarification skills, really great sort
of uh outcome analysis skills like what
outcomes is the customer trying to
achieve, what are the metrics by which
the customer measures success, what's
important to them, what's not important
to them in those outcomes, how can we
communicate to a model in a way that
tells a model what we need it to do and
to meet those requirements because
models will get some of it wrong. Those
are the people are going to be
successful. And in that world, I think
you have big companies like Google and
Meta and so on and Amazon. But you're
going to have 10,000 smaller companies
that are going to now be able to tackle
problems like building software for pet
sitters that never was, you know,
tackled before, you know, or building
software for like doggy daycare. I think
about that because our dog goes to a
doggy daycare and the software just
sucks that they use, right? It's really
bad. that if you have a bunch of domain
experts who can use these tools, now you
have a million small businesses each
solving a problem in a way that's really
perfect for those customers and not
having to worry about the engineering.
Does that make sense? So, it's a
different world. Still a lot of software
engineers, but different skills. What
you said, it sounds like, and I don't
know the product management function uh
description too well, but sounds like it
sounds like someone who's understanding
the customer, the business,
communicating well. It's almost like the
LLM is like a software engineering team,
but it's you know little query engine.
>> It would be like a competent product
manager and and I gotta say like in my
life in my lifetime I've met very few
competent product managers but yes you
could call product manager would be a
good name for it. Yeah. If program
product managers were actually
competent, most of them are not. I got
to say
>> what what makes a competent product
manager by the way.
>> You know, I think a competent product
manager, a lot of them are good at
communicating, although many are not,
but a competent product manager in my
mind is somebody who really understands
again customer outcomes and customer
metrics. So like for instance, if you've
heard of jobs to be done or
outcomedriven innovation, these are
methodologies which are a more
deterministic and and uh than just
touchyfey. So they actually have meth
methodologies where they say this is how
you discover a customer's outcomes like
what what jobs are they trying to get
done during their day where are they
struggling how do they measure success
like what metrics are important to them
like you know maybe you know like for
instance when I'm brushing my teeth I
drool I don't know about you do you
drool when you brush your teeth
>> uh sometimes yes
>> yeah I drool a lot like I just like I
got a lot of saliva okay yeah
>> and for me like one of the really
annoying things about brushing my teeth
is it like
>> like the drool's going all down my arm
and I have to rinse my arm after I brush
and it's like worn everywhere
>> and like that's a that's a metric by
which I judge whether my toothbrush is
great. Of course, I haven't found a good
one. Maybe I should design a toothbrush.
But basically, um you really need to
understand the pains that customers go
through and what they care about and
what's really not that important because
a lot of things that you might think are
important internally customer doesn't
care about. And so I think most most
product managers are touchy feely.
They're like, "Well, I think I know what
the customer wants, and I think I saw a
really cool feature in this product
here, so I'm going to go and do what
they did, but do it a little bit better
without really understanding what the
customer is struggling with. Um, how
often they struggle with that thing. Is
it important to fix or maybe it's not
like, you know, maybe it seems cool to
you and maybe they feature because they
have some extra team members that can do
it, but that's not necessarily the right
thing." And so yes, it would be a very
competent product manager who really
understands the customer, maybe worked
in that environment, knows the problems,
has suffered through the problems, and
can then basically tell LLM how to solve
that problem.
>> I see. So, so competence, if I'm
understanding correctly, is user
empathy. It's knowing what actually
matters uh for them and um building for
that and communicating for that and
measuring that, all those things. But a
lot of people think that's a touchyfey
skill like it's something you just sort
of develop and you sort of have
intuition about the customer. I think it
is a a repeatable process done through
interviews done through observing the
customer. It's not something that you
just sort of get better at by feeling
it. It can be repeated is what I'm
saying. And very few product managers
will do that.
>> I see.
>> Most of them just say, "Oh, I know this
product. I've been working on it for
five years. I know the customer. I
talked to Joe last week at you know
customer name and you know this is what
they really need." Do you really know
that? Like you think you know that, but
what are they trying to get
accomplished?
>> Right. Right.
>> Product managers typically think in
terms of features, not in terms of
customer pain points and what they're
trying to get done.
>> I see.
>> In my in my experience, I'm sure there
are obstructions.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I'm sure there are.
>> I just never met any.
>> Yeah.
Okay. Um, you know, coming to the end of
the interview, I always love reflecting
back on the careers and you've had a
full career at this point, more retired
at this point. Um, so I'm curious like
looking back on your career, is there
anything that you you regret or
something that you wish you would have
changed that maybe others can learn
from?
>> Yeah, I mean a bunch of things I would
say like first of all, I should have
left my job at Semantic earlier. Um, I
feel like you should stay in a job as
long as you are learning new things and
building new skills and as long as you
feel empowered to grow and try things
that might be uncomfortable for you and
not have to worry about your, you know,
what if I fail occasionally, like have
the space to try things and get them
wrong, but to be to be able to create
great things. And I had that during a
lot of my time at Sevantech. But there
was a point where I just wasn't growing
anymore and I was stagnant and I didn't
want to leave. not because, you know, it
was interesting, but because I just
didn't have the confidence to go
somewhere else. And so, I would say
there's a lot of value in staying in a
job as long as you're growing. And that
means maybe switching teams and staying
in the same company. There's a lot of
value of having that institutional
knowledge of a platform that you're
working on or set of systems of your
reputation. Reputation goes a long way.
If you're really good in one in one
area, you switch to another team, you
can use that reputation to help you in
the other area often. Um, and so I think
staying in a job for five years, even 10
years can be, as long as you're
learning, can be really great. I don't
advise people to switch every couple
years necessarily. On the other hand,
you know, staying staying too long, you
know, you can get stale. Um, it gets
easy to just say, you know, I'm
comfortable. I'm not really having to be
challenged. I can do my job. I can wake
up and have some nice coffee in the
morning and I do whatever I do. And it
doesn't really, you know, when you get
more senior, often you can just do that.
And so when you get to that point, it's
time to leave and and challenge yourself
some more. And the problem with that is
when you do leave, you do start over.
Like I found that I had a pretty great
career at Semantic. If you asked anybody
at Semantic from the 21 years I was
there who I was, people would know me.
They'd say hi to me in the hallway. I
even had people come up to me on the
street because I would be on TV talking
about Stuckset and stuff like, you know,
I was on Fox and, you know, MSNBC and
Wall Street Journal, New York Times and
all that stuff. and it was really
exciting. But then you go to Google and
they're like, "What have you done for
us? We don't care that you did those
things. It only matters what you've done
for us." And so that requires a lot of
rebuilding up trust and building up, you
know, sort of a reputation and doing a
lot of good work. And, you know, that's
stressful and it takes a lot more work
than staying where you are. So, if you
do that, got to choose wisely. I hear
I'll probably misattribute who said it,
but there's some quote about you should
either be learning or you should be
earning in your career. Um, what are
your thoughts on your golden handcuffs
somewhere you're no longer learning but
you're earning a ton? Do you would you
still advise that that person leaves?
>> Um, I would never say don't I would
never say leave if there's a a good
package and you know we have to optimize
for multiple things in our life, right?
Learning is definitely important, but
also being financially stable and
different people need different amounts
of money to feel comfortable about being
safe in their life and having enough to
take care of their family or themselves.
I think there's a place for both and it
can be okay to be comfortable and making
a lot of money for a while, but I think
that if you're solving for enjoyment and
fun and hard problem solving, which a
lot of people are, that can be toxic
over too much time.
>> Definitely. It sounds like early in your
career you were lucky to find what you
enjoyed. A lot of those early problems
were super interesting.
>> Yeah.
>> Do you have any advice for people who um
want to find what they enjoy in software
engineering?
>> Yeah, for people who are in college now,
graduating soon. Um I would say like try
lots of internships if you can and that
might be difficult now given the way
things are going with jobs right now.
Everything's cyclical though, but right
now jobs are tough. Um, I found cyber
security entirely randomly. You know, it
wasn't something I was like, I want to
be in cyber security. It's like I had an
internship. My first year was doing file
management. My second year was doing
blah blah blah. Third year, oh, viruses.
The more you can explore, the more
you're going to potentially discover a
passion. And like I think there are many
jobs where you would think it's going to
be totally boring, but if you go and
start working on the problem, you're
going to realize there's really
interesting problems to solve. And you
might find a passion for a field that
you would never expect that you would
enjoy. And then you're like, "Wow, this
is really interesting. There's really
fun problems. I like the people I'm
working with. Customers are
interesting." Or maybe they're a pain in
the ass, but that's interesting to deal
with. Like I would say just try things.
Don't try to wait and find the perfect
job. Find a job that where you have a
good manager. Um there's some hard
problems to solve. Um and um you don't
know anything about it and you'll learn.
Like that's you might find your dream
job and that lesson be 25 years.
>> So before you know what you enjoy,
you're saying, you know, search with
breath and then once you find it, then
you can kind of go deeper.
>> That's right.
>> I mean, look, you might get lucky. If
your first year internship is really
interesting and and you're doing well, I
would stick with that. You could try
breath there, but I would say like a
greedy breath. The last question I have
for you is if you were going to go to
yourself right when you were graduating
from UCLA and give yourself some advice
knowing what you know now, what would
you say?
>> It wouldn't be one thing. I mean, the
biggest thing would be don't let fear of
failure hold you back. You probably can
do more than you think you can do. I
might have had a richer career had I
listened to that. I would say focus on
the outcome. So whenever you're working
on a project, think about who's going to
use it, what do they care about, what
how do they measure success, and then
just optimize for that. And don't like
try to make the perfect thing or try
don't try to make a very, you know,
round thing if all you need is a little
square piece here. Like often problems
can be solved um without having to be
perfect and still be really good. So
like focusing on people's outcomes. Big
one is when you're when you're
presenting, for example, like this had
to learn. I used to go into
presentations and talk about the
technology to senior leaders and like in
retrospect those senior leaders don't
care how the algorithm works. They don't
care. They just want to know is it going
to be faster? How much faster? Is it
going to generate more revenue? How much
revenue? Is it going to, you know, fix a
problem that currently takes 20 people
to do it? Make it 10 people to do it.
And so you really need to get in
people's heads and think about what
they're solving for. Again, this whole
idea of outcomes and then speak to their
needs, not your own. So that's a big
one. I said find a good manager. I'll
just say that again. A manager can make
or break your career and your life and
your like happiness. So, you know, a
good manager that trusts you and gives
you some rope is uh super valuable.
Learn how to collaborate with people.
Just like don't assume that you're right
and just tell people they're wrong. You
have to really learn to work with people
and understand their point of view. I
still struggle at that, but you know,
it's something that's a work in
progress.
>> Those would be big things.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Well, thanks so much,
Carrie, for your time. I really
appreciate it. I was really looking
forward to it. I think there's a lot of
stuff in here that people are going to
benefit from. So, thanks so much for
your time.
>> That was my pleasure.
>> Hey, thanks for watching the show. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to support, you can
subscribe on YouTube or you can leave a
review on Spotify. And I'm always
looking for new guests to interview. So,
if anyone comes up who you think you
really want to hear their career story,
uh, let me know and I'll try to reach
out to them and get them on the show.
Thanks for listening as always and I'll
see you next time.